ILGWU Retiree Service Department, David Dubinsky Papers 5780/099
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Retiree Service Department David Dubinsky Papers
1966-1984
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Dubinsky, David, 1892-1982
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/099
3 cubic feet
3 linear ft.
Records (documents).
This collection contains correspondence, memoranda, vouchers, and other material that document the work of the Department of Retiree Services.
3124474
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
D. Mordente, March 11, 2009
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
The Retiree Services Department was established in October 1966 to provide services to ILGWU members once they retired from the workforce. David Dubinsky served as the founding director of the department, holding the position from retirement from the ILGWU presidency in 1966 until his death in 1982.
The department offered a variety of resources to retirees, including social, recreational and cultural activities, access to a special assistance fund, retirees clubs, and retirement planning services. Local and regional Retiree Clubs were established or further supported through the International's General Office, offering courses and organizing daytrips and other excursions. Through the Retiree Services Department, longtime ILGWU members who found themselves in need could apply for support from the Special Assistance Fund. The department also oversaw the Friendly Visitors Project, which trained retirees to visit other retirees in their home, hospital, or nursing homes. In addition to offering companionship, visitors offered guidance on matters such as Social Security, health care, union benefits, and housing.
The Retiree Services Department continued its work through 1995, when the ILGWU merged with ACTWU to form UNITE. In 1986, it developed the Options for Older Workers to assist workers displaced or shortly to be, plant closings. By the time of the merger, the department had expanded its services and offerings, including English-as-a-Second Language (ESL), an exercise program, acting and arts classes, and volunteer opportunities. The program also helped with retirement planning, and retirees were involved in legislative and election activities.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, memoranda, vouchers, and other material that document the work of the Department of Retiree Services, including requests submitted to the department for funds in support of retiree groups and related activities, and notification of decisions of whether to fund these requests and award amount. Also included are collected printed material and drafts of department publications.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records
International Ladies Garment Workers Union --Sources.
3124474
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Retiree Clubs, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Retiree Clubs, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Retiree Clubs, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Retiree Clubs, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Retiree Clubs, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Miscellaneous [folder 1 of 2], 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Miscellaneous [folder 2 of 2], 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Finance Department, ILGWU. Vouchers, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Finance Department, ILGWU. Vouchers, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Correspondences, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Finance Department, ILGWU. Vouchers., 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Finance Department, ILGWU. Vouchers, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Miscellaneous Information- SSI, Housing, Wills, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Brochure Printing Materials, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Elder Hostel Materials, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Bergen County. Office on Aging, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Report to GEB [folder 1 of 2], 1967-1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Report to GEB [folder 2 of 2], 1967-1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Meeting of the GEB Committee, 1966-1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Minutes of the GEB Committee, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Salary Increases, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Friendly Visiting Service. Staff Memoranda, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Vacation Schedules, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Part-Time Employees, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Dubinsky, David. Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1966-1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Ozone Park Retiree Club, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Friendly Visitors Program [folder 1 of 2], 1967-1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Friendly Visitors Program [folder 2 of 2], 1967-1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Letter to Locals, Re: Special Assistance Fund, 1966-1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Letters to Applicants, Re: Special Assistance Fund, 1999-1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Friendly Visitors Program. Correspondence [folder 1 of 2], 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Friendly Service Program. Correspondence [folder 2 of 2], 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Friendly Visiting in Institutions, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Early Alert Program, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Financial Documents, 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Letters from Retirees, 1967-1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Letters to Retirees, 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Finance Department, ILGWU. Louis Brass-Memoranda and Petty Cash, 1968-1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. General Correspondence, 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Miscellaneous, 1966-1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- New York State Executive Office for the Aging, 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. New York State Vouchers, 1966-1975 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. "After a Life of Labor" Promotion, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Outside of NY Activities, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. "Retired and Remembered" Booklet Materials, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. "Retired and Remembered"- First Draft, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Special Assistance Fund, 1966-1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Special Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. "Retired and Remembered" Acknowledgements, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- New York State Executive Office for the Aging [folder 1 of 2], 1966-1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- New York State Executive Office for the Aging [folder 2 of 2], 1966-1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Foreign Visiting Program Printed Materials, 1967-1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Special Assistance Fund, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Recreational Activities [folder 1 of 2], 1966-1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Recreational Activities [folder 2 of 2] (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Special Assistance Fund, 1966-1971 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare. Administration on Aging, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Special Assistance Fund- Miscellaneous, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Miscellaneous [folder 1 of 2], 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Retiree Service Department, ILGWU. Miscellaneous [folder 2 of 2], 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 15)